Register of the National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies Records, 1939-1946
Hoover Institution Archives
National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies Records,
1939-1946
XX404
National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies
168 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box, 6 envelopes (71.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, statements, pamphlets, serial issues, and photographs, relating to attempts to organize and secure international agreement for a civilian relief program for Norway, Finland, the Netherlands, Belgium, and Poland during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (121 reels).
Access Points
International relief.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Finland.; World War, 1939-1945--Food question.; World War, 1939-1945--Netherlands.; World War, 1939-1945--Norway.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; Belgium.; Finland.; Netherlands.; Norway.; Poland.; United States--Foreign relations.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Kershner, Howard Eldred, 1891-
Historical Note
The presidential election over, we determined that the only way relief could be brought to the women, children, and destitute in the small democracies was to awaken public opinion in the neutral countries to the inconsequential dangers from our proposals. Both the British and Germans were sensitive to neutral opinions. They needed actual support from the neutrals, or at least the continued neutrality of these nations.
On November 18, 1940, we launched an organization called "The National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies." In Addition to myself as Honorary Chairman the original membership comprised those who had taken part in the famine relief of forty five countries after World War I. However, we were soon joined by one thousand leading Americans. The purpose of the committee was: to raise a voice on behalf of Finland, Norway, Holland, Belgium and Central Poland so that agreements may be made by the German and British Governments with a neutral organization--
(a) by which their domestic food supplies can be protected from the occupying armies
(b) by which supplemental supplies can be imported through the German and British blockades and protected
(c) to secure the efficient operation of such a neutral organization.
To the end that the lives of millions of children, women and men can be saved from the inevitable famine and pestilence which confront them, and that renewed hope may be given to them in the ideals of mankind.
I was asking for no gifts, no government appropriations, no use of American ships.
The Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941, brought the United States into the war. Our relief organization had been repudiated by the exiled governments. Now at war, we could not act without the approval of our own government. Our National Committe on Food for the Small Democracies decided to suspend activities, but to resume if opportunity came. We sent word to the exiled governments that, now free from any embarrassment from us, they should secure permission directly to relieve their people at home.
But they got no relief.
It was not until three and one-half years later, when Mr. Truman became President in April, 1945, that American Government policies changed and became compassionate about relief of famine.
From Herbert Hoover, An American Epic, Vol. IV)
Series Description
- OFFICE FILE, 1937-1947. (Boxes 1-41)
  Correspondence, financial records, mailing lists, petitions, press releases, publications and resolutions, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- COMMITTEES, 1939-1945. (Boxes 42-59)
  Correspondence, lists of names of members, memoranda, statements enunciating the NCFSD's policy and program, arranged alphabetically by name of committee and then by physical form
- CHAIRMAN'S FILE, 1938-1946. (Boxes 60-67)
  Papers of Herbert Hoover consisting of correspondence, diaries, history, reports, speeches and writings, statements, and clippings arranged alphabetically by physical form
- MEMBERSHIP, 1939-1946. (Boxes 68-103)
  Correspondence, miscellaneous printed matter, invitations to join, mailing lists and other material related to membership. Includes personal papers of some committee directors. Arranged alphabetically by name of member
- SPEAKERS BUREAU, 1941. (Boxes 104-110)
  Lists of speakers, informative material used by speakers, schedules and correspondence re speaking engagements. Also includes radio programs. Arranged by physical form
- SUPPORT GROUPS, 1940-1946. (Boxes 111-137)
  Correspondence, office files, resolutions and signed petitions, arranged alphabetically by category of support group and then by physical form
- OPPOSITION FILE, 1939-1942. (Boxes 138-139)
  Correspondence, clippings and writings related to individuals and groups engaged in opposition to the work of the committee. Includes material on Dr. Henry Van Dusen. Arranged by physical form
- COUNTRIES FILE, 1933-1948. (Boxes 140-158)
  Correspondence, reports and clippings related to countries receiving aid, requesting aid or establishing contacts with the committee. Arranged alphabetically and therein by physical form
- SUBJECT FILE, 1932-1948. (Boxes 159-166)
  Includes mostly organizations and committes working with the NCFSD or otherwise involved in humanitarian aid. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- MEMORABILIA, n.d. (Box 166)
  One blue and white lapel pin inscribed, "Greek War Relief - I Helped"
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1938?-1941? (Photo file)
  74 prints depicting Howard Kershner, Mr. Hoover's trip to Finland, prominent women, and views of war-torn Norway; and postcards of Belgium, 1940-1941
Container List
- OFFICE FILE, 1937-1947.
  Files of the National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies, parent organization comprised of three committees: the Executive Committee headed by Mr. Hoover; a National Committee of leading Americans who lent their names and influence; and the Local Committees, headed by community leaders throughout the United States who caused supportive resolutions to be written and petitions to be signed
  - Administrative file
    - Addressograph Multigraph Company contracts (Box 1., Folder 1)
    - Building directory information (Folder 2)
    - Leases (Folder 3)
    - Letterheads (Folder 4)
    - Reports (Folder 5)
  - Airline travel information (Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1941-1944 (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence file, 1937-1945. Includes reports and miscellaneous printed matter
    - General (Folder 8)
      - General. Letters to refute misinformation about the NCFSD (Folder 9)
      - Alphabetical
        - General
          - A (Folder 10)
          - Ba-Bn (Folder 11)
          - Bo-Bu (Box 2., Folder 1)
          - C (Folder 2-3)
          - D (Folder 4)
          - E (Folder 5)
          - F (Folder 6)
          - G (Folder 7)
          - H (Box 3., Folder 1-3)
          - I (Folder 4)
          - J (Folder 5)
          - K (Folder 6-7)
          - L (Folder 8-9)
          - Mc (Box 4., Folder 1)
          - Ma-Mh (Folder 2)
          - Mi-Mn (Folder 3-4)
          - Mo-Mz (Folder 5)
          - N (Folder 6)
          - O (Folder 7)
          - P (Folder 8)
          - Ra-Rn (Box 5., Folder 1)
          - Ro-Rz (Folder 2)
          - Sa-Sd (Folder 3)
          - Se-Sm (Folder 4)
          - Sn-St (Folder 5)
          - Su-Sz (Folder 6)
          - T (Folder 7)
          - U-V (Folder 8)
          - Wa-Wh (Box 6., Folder 1)
          - Wi-Wz (Folder 2-3)
          - Y (Folder 4)
          - Z (Folder 5)
        - Agar, Herbert and William (Folder 6)
        - Allen, Ben (Folder 7)
        - Allen, Dorothy (Folder 8)
        - Anderson. Includes all members with the surname Anderson (Folder 9)
        - Archawski, Waldemar (Folder 10)
        - Baker, Albert (Folder 11)
        - Ball, William (Folder 12)
        - Barber, Maurice (Folder 13)
        - Beebee, Gertrude (Folder 14)
        - Bell, B. Tartt (Folder 15)
        - Bell, H. C. F. (Folder 16)
        - Bigwood, E. J. Includes "Bigwood Report" and miscellaneous related material (Box 7., Folder 1-3)
        - Blake, James (Folder 4)
        - Bloem, P. J. L. de (Folder 5)
        - Blumenthal, Morton (Folder 6)
        - Bonde, Knut, Baron (Folder 7)
        - Bonney, Therese (Folder 8)
        - Brewster, Edward (Folder 9)
        - Briggs, Thomas (Folder 10)
        - Brittain, Vera (Folder 11)
        - Brook, Roger (Folder 12)
        - Brown. Includes all members with the surname Brown (Folder 13)
        - Burkick, Fred (Folder 14)
        - Burton, R. B. (Folder 15)
        - Canterbury, Archbishop of (Box 8., Folder 1)
        - Cardwell, Ann (Folder 2)
        - Carrel, Alexis (Folder 3)
        - Castle, William (Folder 4)
        - Chenery, William (Folder 5)
        - Churchill, Winston (Folder 6)
        - Clapp, Paul (Folder 7)
        - Clapper, Raymond (Folder 8)
        - Clark, Glenn (Folder 9)
        - Coffin, Henry Sloane (Folder 10)
        - Cross, Harry (Folder 11)
        - Cudahy, John (Folder 12-14)
        - Davies. Includes all members with the surname Davies (Folder 15)
        - Davis, J. (Folder 16)
        - Dennis, Lawrence (Folder 17)
        - Denny, Ludwell (Folder 18)
        - Detzer, Dorothy (Folder 19)
        - Drucker, Peter (Folder 20)
        - Duncan, Frances (Folder 21)
        - Flewell, Edith (Folder 22)
        - Fritz, Beulah (Folder 23)
        - Fry, Varian (Folder 24)
        - Gillett, E. K. (Folder 25)
        - Goerter, Daniel de (Folder 26)
        - Griggs, Julian (Folder 27)
        - Hambro, Carl (Box 9., Folder 1)
        - Handsaker, J. J. (Folder 2)
        - Herter, Christian (Folder 3)
        - Heyl, Ernest (Folder 4)
        - Hillsmith, Clarence (Folder 5)
        - Irwin, Will (Folder 6)
        - Janney, John (Folder 7)
        - Johnson, J. W. (Folder 8)
        - Johnson. Includes all members with the surname Johnson (Folder 9)
        - Larsen, Carl (Folder 10)
        - Lipsett, Alexander (Folder 11)
        - Lindbergh, Anne and Charles (Folder 12)
        - Lochner, Louis (Folder 13)
        - Loewenstein, Hubertus, Prince (Folder 14)
        - Luce, Clare Boothe (Folder 15)
        - Lutz, Ralph (Folder 16)
        - McCormick, Anne O'Hare (Folder 17)
        - McGeachy, Mary Craig (Folder 18)
        - Moen, Lars (Folder 19)
        - Morgan, Ann (Folder 20)
        - O'Brien, Daniel (Box 10., Folder 1)
        - Pennock, Meta (Folder 2)
        - Previtali, Rose (Folder 3)
        - Redfern, Gilbert (Folder 4)
        - Rickard, Edgar (Folder 5)
        - Richardson, John (Folder 6)
        - Sawtelle, Raymond (Folder 7)
        - Shattuck, Edwin (Folder 8)
        - Shaler, Millard (Folder 9)
        - Sokolsky, George (Folder 10)
        - Stowe, Leland (Folder 11)
        - Strauss, Lewis (Folder 12)
        - Thelen, John (Folder 13)
        - Thompson, Dorothy (Folder 14)
        - Tolles, Louis (Folder 15)
        - Tomara, Sonia (Folder 16)
        - Topping, Tom (Folder 17)
        - Torrey, Clare (Folder 18)
        - Wilbur, Marvin (Folder 19)
      - Chronological
        - 1939 (Folder 20)
        - 1939-1940 September 30 (Folder 21)
        - 1940
          - January-March (Folder 22)
          - April-June (Folder 23)
          - July (Folder 24)
          - August (Box 11., Folder 1)
          - September (Folder 2)
          - October (Folder 3)
          - October 2-November 19 (Folder 4)
          - November (Folder 5)
          - November 20-December 6 (Folder 6)
          - December (Folder 7)
          - December 7-December 31
        - 1941
          - January (Box 12., Folder 1)
          - February (Folder 2)
          - March (Folder 3)
          - April (Folder 4)
          - May (Folder 5)
          - June (Folder 6)
          - July-August (Folder 7)
          - September (Box 13., Folder 1)
          - October (Folder 2)
          - November-December (Folder 3)
        - 1941-1944 (Folder 4)
        - 1942 (Folder 5)
        - 1943-1945 (Folder 6)
    - Cables
      - General, 1939-1941. Lists of cables
        - Incoming (Box 14., Folder 1-2)
        - Outgoing (Folder 3)
      - Berlin, 1941 (Folder 4)
      - Denmark, Norway, and Paris, 1940-1941 (Folder 5)
      - Heyl, Ernest and Raymond Wilson, 1940 (Folder 6)
      - Lithuania, 1940 (Folder 7-8)
      - London, 1940-1941 (Folder 9)
      - McDonald (?), 1941 (Folder 10)
      - Stephens, Dorsey, 1940 (Folder 11)
      - Sweden, 1940 (Folder 12)
  - Financial records
    - Auditing firm file
      - General (Box 15., Folder 1)
      - Statements of receipts and disbursements (Folder 2)
    - Bank accounts
      - Bankers Trust Company (Folder 3)
      - The Chase National Bank (Folder 4)
      - The First National Bank of Boston (Folder 5)
      - Guaranty Trust Company (Folder 6)
      - National City Bank of New York (Folder 7)
    - Budget file, 1941-1943 (Folder 8)
    - Expenses
      - 1940 (Folder 9)
      - 1941 (Folder 10)
      - 1942 (Folder 11)
    - Liquidation papers (Folder 12)
    - Tax forms (Folder 13)
  - Insurance correspondence and contracts (Folder 14)
  - Mailing lists, 1941
    - Names of people interested in the NCFSD, some with street addresses, arranged by state
      - Alabama to Minnesota (Box 16., Folder 1)
      - Mississippi to Wyoming (Folder 2)
    - Names and hometown or city of local chairmen, arranged by state
      - Alabama to Missouri (Folder 3)
      - Montana to Wyoming (Folder 4)
    - Names of residents in 46 states and the District of Columbia (supplemental mailing list of 612) (Folder 5)
  - Memoranda (Folder 6)
  - Petitions
    - Alabama (Box 17., Folder 1)
    - Arizona (Folder 2)
    - Arkansas (Folder 3)
    - California (Folder 4)
    - Colorado and Connecticut (Folder 5)
    - Delaware and District of Columbia (Folder 6)
    - Georgia, Florida, and Idaho (Folder 7)
    - Illinois (Folder 8)
    - Illinois (Box 18., Folder 1-2)
    - Indiana (Folder 3)
    - Iowa (Folder 4)
    - Kansas and Kentucky (Folder 5)
    - Kentucky (Box 19., Folder 1)
    - Louisiana (Folder 2)
    - Maine (Folder 3)
    - Maryland (Folder 4)
    - Massachusetts (Folder 5-7)
    - Michigan (Folder 8)
    - Minnesota (Box 20., Folder 1)
    - Mississippi (Folder 2)
    - Missouri (Folder 3)
    - Montana (Folder 4)
    - Nebraska (Folder 5)
    - Nevada (Folder 6)
    - New Jersey (Folder 7)
    - New Hampshire (Folder 8)
    - New Mexico (Folder 9)
    - New York (Folder 10)
    - North Carolina (Box 21., Folder 1)
    - North Dakota (Folder 2)
    - Ohio (Folder 3)
    - Oklahoma (Folder 4)
    - Oregon (Folder 5)
    - Pennsylvania (Folder 6-8)
    - Rhode Island (Box 22., Folder 1)
    - South Carolina (Folder 2)
    - South Dakota (Folder 3)
    - Tennessee (Folder 4)
    - Texas (Folder 5)
    - Utah (Folder 6)
    - Vermont (Folder 7)
    - Virginia (Folder 8)
    - Washington (Folder 9)
    - West Virginia (Folder 10)
    - Wisconsin (Folder 11)
    - Wyoming (Folder 12)
  - Public relations file, 1938-1947
    - General (Box 23., Folder 1)
    - Advertisements and correspondence of printing company (Folder 2)
    - Chronological list of press releases and publications issued and speeches and statements given entitled "History of the National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies," (Folder 3)
    - Clippings about various World War II relief projects, including NCFSD
      - 1939-1940 August 13 (Folder 4)
      - 1940 August 14 - December (Folder 5)
      - 1941
        - January-June (Folder 6)
        - July-December (Box 24., Folder 1)
      - 1942-1945 (Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1941
      - Form letters from Charles F. Horner, Director, Local Committees (Folder 3)
      - Letters to Mr. Hoover in opposition to NCFSD and replies from Bernice Miller, 1940 August (Folder 4)
      - Letters and bulletins to chairmen of local committees
        - Undated (Box 25., Folder 1)
        - 1941
          - January 15, 22, 29 (Folder 2)
          - February 5, 8, 19, 24 (Folder 3)
          - March 3, 5, 11, 28 (Folder 4)
          - April 10, 21 (Folder 5)
          - May 17 (Folder 6)
          - June 17, 19, 24 (Folder 7)
          - July 2 (Folder 8)
          - August 4, 20 (Folder 9)
          - September 10, 24 (Folder 10)
          - October 9, 29 (Folder 11)
          - November 29 (Folder 12)
          - December 27 (Folder 13)
      - Letters to National Committee members
        - 1940 October-1941 February (Folder 14)
        - 1941
          - March (Folder 15)
          - April-December (Folder 16)
      - Requests for NCFSD publications
        - College and university libraries (Folder 17)
        - Public libraries (Folder 18)
    - Press releases, statements, broadcast transcripts, bulletins
      - Undated (Box 26., Folder 1)
      - 1938-1940 (Folder 2)
      - 1941 January-March (Folder 3)
      - 1941 April-1945 (Folder 4)
    - Publications
      - "An Alternative Suggestion," n.d. Statement. Typescript (Box 27., Folder 1)
      - "The American Campus Speaks," 1941 April 20. Radio broadcast transcript. Typescript (Folder 2)
      - "Blockade Means Starving Babies," n.d. Excerpts from Unfinished Victory by Arthur Bryant. Typescript (Folder 3)
      - British Attitude Toward the Relief of Belgium During German Occupation in the First World War, 1940 December. Two printed brochures (Folder 4)
      - "British Statements Regarding the Continental Food Problem," 1941 February 28. Two typescript copies (Folder 5)
      - "The Challenge to Christianity," n.d. Two posters (Folder 6)
      - "Compassion in Conflict," n.d. Radio talk by Governor Leverett Saltonstall. Typescript (Folder 7)
      - Essay by Rose Wilder Lane, n.d. Typescript (Folder 8)
        - "The Evidence," 1941. Two printed flyers (Folder 9)
      - Facing the Facts, 1941 March 15 - November 27. Twenty-four printed issues (Folder 10)
      - "Facts and Purposes of the National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies," n.d. (Folder 11)
      - Statement of explanation of formation includes historical perspective, endorsements, list of supporting clergymen and a description of the campaign to import food to some European countries. Typescript
      - Food Aid Appeals From the Small Democracies, 1941. Two printed pamphlets (Folder 12)
      - "Food for the Small Democracies: The Needs," 1941 ? Two typescript copies (Folder 13)
      - Food map of Europe, 1941. Three printed copies (Folder 14)
      - The Food Situation in Belgium as of July 1941, by E. J. Bigwood, with forward by Herbert Hoover, 1941. Two printed copies (Folder 15)
      - "God and My Grandmother," n.d. Essay by Alice Booth. Typescript (Folder 16)
      - Letter sent to the 9 Philadelphians, 1940 October. Typescript (Folder 17)
      - Manual of Simple Procedure for Local Activity for National Committee on Food for the Five Small Democracies, n.d. Includes a list of the material available, samples of a resolution, endorsement and a letter. Typescript and four printed pamphlets (Folder 18)
      - The March of Hunger, n.d. Script for a 5 minute radio broadcast. Typescript (Folder 19)
      - Must They Starve? 1940 October. Pamphlet responds to questions and answers from The Christian Science Monitor. Two printed pamphlets, two typescript copies of questions, four posters (two with cover letters), memoranda, correspondence (Folder 20)
      - Must They Starve?1940 October. Pamphlet that is a literal and idiomatic translation of that described above, into Yiddish, with a forward, appeal for support, and a different photograph. Issued by NCFSD's Jewish Participation Bureau. Three printed pamphlets and a memorandum (Folder 21)
      - "No Food Wasted, None Stolen or Lost," 1941. Two printed flyers (Folder 22)
      - Plan For Saving Lives... 1941. Three printed brochures (Folder 23)
      - "Some Comments on the Food Situation in Germany and the Occupied Countries," n.d. Two typescript statements (Folder 24)
      - "Stark Rations," n.d. Printed flyer, one newspaper mat (Folder 25)
      - "Statement by (the) Executive Committee of the National Committee on Food for the Five Small Democracies," 1940. Two printed brochures explaining the reason for formation of the NCFSD (Folder 26)
      - "Statement by (the) Executive Committee of (the) National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies, 1941 February 20, refuting objections to the NCFSD. Typescript (Folder 27)
      - "Statement by the Executive Committee of the National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies, in Reply to the Statement of the British Ambassador of March 10th, 1941," n.d. One printed copy and one typescript copy of the British press release (Folder 28)
      - "Synopsis. The Case for the Small Democracies," 1941 April 3. Two typescript copies (Folder 29)
      - "Synopsis of Pros and Cons," n.d. Two typescript copies (Folder 30)
      - "We as Americans..." Memorandum issued 1940 September, October and November, with same text. Three printed copies (Folder 31)
      - "What Must Be Done to Start Relief," 1943 May 3. Two typescript copies (Folder 32)
      - "Why I Support the Hoover Plan," n.d. Statement by Inez Haynes Irwin (Folder 33)
    - Publicity file from other sources. Articles, editorials, speeches, pamphlets and press releases supporting the NCFSD
      - 1940
        - General (Box 28., Folder 1)
        - Letters to Hoover, June-July (Folder 2)
      - 1941 (Folder 3)
      - 1942 (Folder 4)
      - 1943 (Folder 5)
    - Resolutions, 1941-1942
      - General
        - General (Box 29., Folder 1)
        - Status of tabulations
          - Carded complete (Folder 2)
          - Not counted (Folder 3)
          - Received after January 1, 1942 (Folder 4)
          - Reports re endorsement of resolutions by state, city, town, and organization
            - Undated (Folder 5)
            - 1941
              - March 25 (Folder 6)
              - April 23 (Folder 7)
          - To be checked and carded (Folder 8)
          - To be checked for tabulation (Folder 9)
      - Signed pledges of support of the NCFSD, specifically of aid to Poland, from U.S. Polish organizations, 1941 February-April. An acknowledgement written in Polish accompanies each "Approval" sheet
        - Connecticut (Box 30., Folder 1)
        - Illinois (Folder 2)
        - Indiana (Folder 3)
        - Massachusetts (Folder 4)
        - Michigan (Folder 5)
        - Minnesota (Folder 6)
        - New Jersey (Folder 7)
        - New York (Folder 8)
        - Ohio (Folder 9)
        - Pennsylvania (Folder 10)
        - Wisconsin (Folder 11)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 12)
      - Signed endorsement forms, many with correspondence attached
        - Unsorted (Box 31., Folder 1)
        - Alabama (Folder 2)
        - Arizona (Folder 3)
        - Arkansas (Folder 4)
        - California (Folder 5)
        - Colorado (Folder 6)